Akarsh Bachu

Data Scientist

Skilled in developing end-end Data Science applications with 3.5+ years of experience. Achievements include developing a Merchant Location Cleaning application that involves the prediction of Brand and Location from messy bank transactions with an accuracy of 0.96, thereby generating revenue to our company and receiving a 5-star performance rating for the same.



bachu.akarsh@gmail.com

7729862404

Hyderabad, India

akarsh.netlify.app/

linkedin.com/in/akarshbachu in

github.com/akarshbachu ()

WORK EXPERIENCE

Associate Data Scientist Cardlytics Inc.

05/2020 - Present

Cardlytics is into Purchase Intelligence, Based on transaction data from banks we generate offers and these offers are placed on the user's bank portal.

Description/Responsibilities

- Predicting Brand name from the given messy transaction data using C-CNN model, which gave an accuracy of 0.96 for 12k brands.
- Mapping this transaction data to store location at various confidence levels like street, zip, and city-level with an accuracy of 0.85-0.95 based on the brand and information from the transaction using cascading C-CNN models.
- Developed this application with minimum guidance from the product team, application life cycle involves EDA, Preprocessing, building models, exposing this a service using FLASK with Gunicorn WSGI HTTP server and deployed on Kubernetes cluster to handle multiple requests, which can clean 24 Million transactions per day.
- Automated train, test pipeline with a Cron job, Created dashboards in sumo logic and Datadog based on the application logs to monitor the performance of the application.

Jr. Data Scientist & Java Dev ADP India Pvt Ltd

08/2017 - 05/2020

The Product Provides Analytics of various other Products of ADP, Using Dashboards, KPI's(Key Performance Indicators) Benchmarks, and Explorers.

Description/Responsibilities

- Involved in all phases of Data Science and ML tasks like Data Preprocessing, EDA, Visualization, Feature Engineering, Developing Models, and Validation.
- Recommending insights based on the user interaction, Used Random Forest classifier to classify insights as liked or disliked i.e. converted recommendation problem to classification problem.
- Performed Machine Learning tasks to predict the turnover of an employee, achieved AUC of 0.88 using XGBoost.
- Creating KPIs (Key Performance Indicators) using Java and JPA Framework(myBatis) and developed API for exposing it.

EDUCATION

M.Sc in Data Science
Liverpool John Moores University

07/2019 - 05/2021

Thesis

 Thesis on Character Level Convolutions for Text

SKILLS



PERSONAL PROJECTS

StackOverFlow Tag Predictor (10/2020)

 As part of the thesis, experimenting Character Level CNN model with dynamic sized filters to predict tags for the given question.

Data Augmentation with GAN (08/2020 - 08/2020)

 In the Credit Card fraud dataset there are only 0.017% of fraud transactions, so balanced the data using GAN and performed classification using Random Forest which gave a recall of 0.98 for Class 1.

Stock Price Prediction (05/2019 - 05/2019)

 It's a Deep Learning Model, that predicts the stock price of (n+1)th day given n days data with features like Stock Metadata, the Volatility index, Nifty Index, Nasdaq Index, etc. using LSTM.

Donors Choose Application Screening (11/2018 - 12/2018)

 It's a Classification problem where the model classifies if the project proposed can be Approved or not, Achieved an AUC of 0.74 using LightGBM.

Netflix Movie Recommendation Engine (08/2018 - 08/2018)

 It's a Machine Learning Model that recommends the movies by analyzing user's previous history.

Personal Website (02/2018 - 02/2018)

 It's a Personal Portfolio created using HTML and Bootstrap, includes a Chat-bot (Virtual Representation of Me).

Heart Connoisseur (05/2016 - 06/2016)

 It's an IOT based alarming device built for detecting heart abnormalities that also notifies the pre-chosen contacts for help in the span of an SMS.

ACHIEVEMENTS

Star performer of Data Science team - Y20

Oracle Certified Java Programmer

Oracle Testing Id: OC1731881 (Java SE 8)

Hackerrank Algorithm Level 5

Received a Merit certificate from ICSI for presenting 'Heart Connoisseur'(IOT project)